Guide to the James A. Flint Papers 1897-1923
Montana Historical Society Archives
James A. Flint Papers
1897-1923
Montana Historical Society, Research Center Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-4774 mhslibrary@mt.gov
MC 229
Flint, James A., 1867-1956
1 linear feet of shelf space
This collection (1880's-1920s) consists of documents accumulated by James Flint in his role as a U.S. Land Commissioner, including letters, homestead forms, and information regarding homestead claims and titles during his tenure in that capacity.
James A. Flint was born on May 28, 1867 in Westminister, Vermont, the son of James Johnson Flint and Ellen Susan Marcy Flint. At the age of 21, Flint entered the Kansas University at Lawrence where he earned a law degree. During the 1890s, he opened a law office in Lawrence and practiced there until 1899 when he began travelling. In the fall of 1900 Flint came to Butte, Montana, but stayed less than a year leaving the following spring for Pony, where he established a law office. Shortly thereafter, he entered into a partnership with Charles Morris under the name of Morris and Flint, a firm specializing in mining, real estate, assaying, and insurance. In 1902, Flint was appointed by the Department of the Interior to succeed A.W. Noyes as U.S. Land Commissioner for Madison and Gallatin counties. Flint served in this position for nearly fifteen years. Flint was an active member of the Pony community taking an interest in school issues and serving on the town council. From 1928 to 1943 he operated a law office in Three Forks. Flint retired in 1944 and died on September 2, 1956.
Content Description:
This collection has been arranged in five series: General Correspondence, Miscellaneous Correspondence, Court Papers, Homestead Case Files, and Homestead Miscellany. _ The General Correspondence (1902-1917) to and from Flint, regards homestead claims, applications, and other legal business pertaining to land ownership. The Miscellaneous Correspondence (1897-1910) is to A.W. Noyes, Flint's predecessor as Land Commissioner. The Court Papers are (1908-1910) composed of legal briefs, arranged alphabetically. The Homestead Case Files (1900-1923), also arranged alphabetically, consist of affidavits, claims, petitions, land diagrams, and witness testimony. Homestead Miscellany (1911-1917) contains pamphlets, receipts, blank forms, and unidentified land diagrams.
Arrangement:
by series
Acquisition Information:
available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Land tenure--Montana--Gallatin County; Land tenure--Montana--Madison County; Homesteading--Montana--Gallatin County; Homesteading--Montana--Madison County; Madison County (Mont.); Gallatin County (Mont.); Montana; Agriculture
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- General Correspondence
  - Chronological (correspondents include United States Land Office, Helena [Frank D. Miracle]; United States Land Office, Bozeman [M.R. Wilson and F.W. Appleton]; Northern Pacific Railway Company; H.A. Bolinger; Anna Richter; George B. Hadzor; Elsie Johnston), 1902-1917, n.d. (Box-folder 1 / 1-3)
  - Re: Fred Morris case, 1907; 1913-1914; 1916 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - Montana, Wyoming and Southern Railway Company, 1901-1910 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence
  - Correspondence to A.W. Noyes (U.S. Land Office commissioner at Pony) from various individuals, 1899-1902 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
- Court Papers
  - John C. Ramsey vs. Arthur Lisbony (before U.S. Land Office, Bozeman), 1911;1917 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - Josiah D. Reed vs. John Vanderbilt (before U.S. Land Office, Bozeman), 1908 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
- Homestead Case Files
  - A-Bl (includes John W. Alexander, Ella Andrews, Oliver Andrews, Albert Edson Barter, George T. Bennett, Abner J. Benson, Mary P. Benson, John S. Black), 1904-1918 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - Bog-Box (includes Tony O.H. Bogalsky, Jesse S. Bosworth, John Bosworth, William N. and Elsie Bowman), 1914-1918 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - Br-Bu (includes Luke W. Brady, David Bryant, Charley A. Burrell), 1908-1915 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - Ca-Cl (includes John W. Caddell, Samuel J.T. Cade, John Carey, Ethel Carmichael, John L. Carter, William L. Carter, Edwin Casson, Martha Christenot, Albert F. Church, Mary A. Cleveland), 1913-1916 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
  - Co-Cu (includes Sarah Comer, Thomas Comer, Michael L. Connor, William H. Copeland, Clarence R. Courtney, Charles Cowdrey, James Cummings), 1913-1917 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
  - D (includes Alvah Davis, William Deascey, Charles D. DeFrance, William E. Divine, John W. Drake, Woodman B. Durgin, Samuel G. Durham), 1908-1911 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
  - E (includes Hermon E. Earle, John Elliott), 1904-1915 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - Fa-Fl (includes Maggie J. Fain, Andrew M. Ferguson, Jefferson D. Ferguson, Roland Ferguson, Clara Ferguson, Joseph Ferrell, Albert F. Fisher, Mary A. Fisher, William B. Fisher, William J. Fitzhugh, Julia E. Fletcher), 1903-1916 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
  - Fo-Fr (includes Commodore D. Foster, Edgar [or Edwin] M. Freeman, Robert L. Freeman), 1916-1917 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
  - Ga-Gi (Charles Gardner, John W. Gardner, John H. Gibson, Byr Franklin Gilbert, Elijah S. Gilliam, Roy M. Gilliam, Elise Girard [Belisle], Ezechias Girard), 1910-1917 (Box-folder 1 / 18)
  - Go-Gr (includes Louis Goerner, Wesley Gourdier, Peter Grant, Frank Griebel, John C. Grove Jr.), 1904-1905 (Box-folder 1 / 19)
  - H (includes George B. Hadzor, Robert C. Hadzor, Jacob Hain, Joe Hain, Mary J. Hammill, Jacob J. Heck, Earl Hilderbrand, Alfred Hiscock), 1903-1910 (Box-folder 1 / 20)
  - I (includes Jacob Igleheart, Samuel D. Igleheart, Edmond J. Irwin, Nicklos G. Irwin), 1912-1916 (Box-folder 1 / 21)
  - Ja (includes Bert E. Jackson, Emily Jackson, John T. Jackson, Micajah W. Jackson, Peter V. Jackson, Frank Janiszewski, Ella Janney), 1903-1923 (Box-folder 2 / 1-3)
  - Jo-Ju (includes Benet H. Johns, Henry K. Johnson, James B. Johnson, John Johnson, Archer F. Johnston, Joseph Johnston, Ray Johnston, Royce L. Johnston, Fred S. Johnstone, Evert W. Jones, Alexander Juday), 1902-1921 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
  - K (includes Anna Kaiser, William A. Kelly, Jonas W. Knight, Walter N. Knight, Herbert F. Kuethe), 1915 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
  - L (includes Daniel H. Lake, John Lally, Andrew J. LaMar, Patrick Lamb, Leo H. Lau, Henry B. Lent, Charles F. Linebarger, Louis Locke, Albert Luik, William Luik), 1905-1917 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
  - Ma-Mc (includes Glenn W. Madison, Albert J. Mallow, Margaret M. Manley, Wilford D. Manley, Lewis E. Marshall, Lee Martin, John W. Mattice, Catherine McGrath, William McGrath, Charles B. McKinney, George H. McLean, James McNett), 1901-1916 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
  - Mi (includes Cortland P. Milgate, Albert H. Miller, Carl Miller, Louise Miller), 1901-1916 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
  - Mo-My (includes Eva K. Moger, William M. Moore, Charles E. Morris, Smiley P. Morris, Soren Mortensen, William L. Mull, Daniel W. Munro, Thomas J. Murphy, Frank C. Myers), 1909-1917 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
  - N (includes Hans Nelson, Mrs. Charles Newkirk, O.F. Newkirk, Denzil J. Nicholson, Alvin Noble, Clifford Noble, John Northey), 1914-1919 (Box-folder 2 / 10)
  - Pa (includes Alfred E. Parent, Edward J. Parent, Aden W. Paris, Wilder B. Parker, Almond Patrick, Edwin T. Patrick, James H. Patrick, Leonard H. Patrick, Ulysses G. Patrick, Mary A. Paul), 1900-1917 (Box-folder 2 / 11)
  - Ph-Pu (includes Robert J. Philpott, George W. Pope, James S. Powell, John W. Powell, Benjamin S. Priest, William A. Priest, William W. Priest, Berthold F. Purdom, George S. Purdom, William T. Purdom), 1903-1917 (Box-folder 2 / 12)
  - Ra-Re (includes William D. Ramey, William E. Reed, Charles H. Reid, John Reid, William Reynolds), 1905-1918 (Box-folder 2 / 13)
  - Ri-Ru (includes Richard A. Richter, Earl W. Roadarmel, Rose M. Roberts, George B. Rowe, Richard Royston, Glenn M. Rundell, Henry M. Rundell, William R. Rundell), 1906-1917 (Box-folder 2 / 14)
  - S-T (includes William H. Schamp, Mark Selway, James A. Shad, Zalmer A. Short, Joseph Sicard, Anna C. Smith, Harry G. Smith, Thomas W. Smith, Lillie A. Strong, Squire T. Summers, Jeff Sutton, Harry R. Thixton, Eugene Tinder), 1902-1912 (Box-folder 2 / 15)
  - W (includes Margaret P. Weaver, Hiram Williams, Lillie Woolsey, William B. Woolsey), 1904-1916 (Box-folder 2 / 16)
  - Y (includes Hilda Young, John O. Young, William Ira Young), 1915-1916 (Box-folder 2 / 17)
- Miscellany
  - Pamphlets, blank forms, receipts, unidentified land diagrams, 1911-1917 (Box-folder 2 / 18)